Guide to the Peter Hellyer papers AD.MC.068
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Natural history and wildlife conservation, 1984-2020
  - Emirates Natural History Group: Hellyer, Peter, ed. "The Natural History of Merawah Island, Abu Dhabi, UAE. An interim report prepared for H.E. Major General Sheikh Mohammed bin Zayed al Nahyan", June 1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - ERWDA: "A Proposal to Establish the Umm al Zummoul National Park", June 2003 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - ERWDA: "The Vegetation of Al Wathba Wetland Reserve" [report], January 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Geology: Buhais Geology Park, Sharjah. Architect's prospectus, 2020 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Geology: fragment from untitled guidebook, about geology of Musandam Peninsula (C.U. Crausaz), undated, circa 1980s (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Geology: Crausaz, C. "Jabal Ghawil. Geologic Guidebook, Northern Oman Mountains, Buraimi-Hatta area." ADCO, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Reports, general: Lancaster, William and Fidelity. "Tree cores from Ras al-h/aymah...", undated, circa 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Reports, general: Natural History Museum of London. "Palaeontological and Geological Study on the Miocene Rocks of the Western Region...", July 1994 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Reprints: Aspinall and Hellyer: "Saline Wetland Reserve Management: a case study from the United Arab Emirates" in Sabkha Ecosystems, pages 335-340 (Kluwer), 2002 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Reprints: Evans, Graham. "The Arabian Gulf: a Modern Carbonate-Evaporate Factory, a Review" (copy inscribed to Peter Hellyer), Cuadernos de Geologia Iberica, No. 19, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Topical: Al Ain Zoo: articles, correspondence, documents, 1996-1998 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Topical: Al Ain Zoo: "Report on the Management of the Al Ain Zoological Park," by David M. Jones, May 1998 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Topical: Federal Law No. (24) of 1999, for the Protection and Development of the Environment (photocopy), 2000 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Newspapers and media, 1985-2013
  - Coverage of Sarah Balabagan case, folder 1, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Coverage of Sarah Balabagan case, folder 2, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Coverage of Sarah Balabagan case, folder 3, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Coverage of Sarah Balabagan case, folder 4, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Coverage of Sarah Balabagan case, folder 5, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Transcript of recorded interview with Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan, undated, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Emirates News: entertainment and social columns, under byline of "Man Siarad", 1987-1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Emirates News: coverage of British politics, 1992-1997 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Emirates News: columns by Peter Hellyer, 1994-1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Emirates News: selected feature articles by Peter Hellyer, 1987-1993 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Emirates News: selected feature articles by Peter Hellyer, 1995-1998 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Emirates News: selected features, by others, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Emirates News: selected obituaries, 1989-1996 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Emirates News: visit of Wilfred Thesiger to UAE, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Emirates News, entire newspaper: Vol. 21, No. 1, pages 1-12: "Another milestone...in the great march" [lead story, National Day 1991], December 2, 1991 (Box OS-1, Folder 1)
  - Emirates News, special supplement: "2 Golden Decades" [twentieth anniversary of the UAE], December 2, 1991 (Box OS-1, Folder 2)
  - Emirates News, entire newspaper, Vol. 22, No. 1: "Yet another milestone; rulers, Crown Prince, world leaders greet President..." [National Day 1992], Dec. 2, 1992 (Box OS-1, Folder 3)
  - Emirates News, special supplement, "On to 22..." [Twenty-First National Day anniversary], December 2, 1992 (Box OS-1, Folder 4)
  - Emirates News, special supplements: "31: Happy Anniversary" [Accession Day], undated, August 1997 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Emirates News, special supplements: "26: Another Year to Celebrate" [National Day], undated, December 1997 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Emirates News, entire newspaper, last issue, Vol. 28, No. 46: "GCC shocked by Iraqi provocations", January 16, 1999 (Box OS-1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper sections: City Times (supplement to Khaleej Times), Vol. 3, Issue 199: "Country Descends Into a Pall of Gloom..."[announcement of death of Sheikh Zayed], November 3, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper sections: City Times (supplement to Khaleej Times), Vol. 3, Issue 200: "Nation Bids Leader a Tearful Farewell", November 4, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper sections: City Times (supplement to Khaleej Times), Vol. 3, Issue 202: "Arab stars lament Shaikh Zayed's loss", November 6, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: Supplement, "UAE National Day", December 2, 1990 (Box OS-1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: "Shaikh Zayed, 1918-2004: Nation Mourns Leader", November 3, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: "Khalifa elected President after Zayed is laid to rest", November 4, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: "Shaikh Zayed: The nation pays tribute and says farewell" [special supplement, containing formal condolences], November 4, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: "Chirac offers condolences: leaders offer sympathies to Khalifa...", November 6, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper sections: Gulf News: "Diplomats and UAE officials call on Khalifa", November 7, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper sections: The Gulf Today, Vol. 9, No. 204: "Farewell to Zayed", November 3, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper sections: The Gulf Today, Vol. 9, No. 207: "Tributes Pour in for Sheikh Zayed", November 6, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper sections: The Gulf Today, Vol. 9, No. 208: "Citizens, residents offer condolences", November 7, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, Vol. XIII, No. 110: "Iraqi troops march into Kuwait", August 3, 1990 (Box OS-1, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, pages 21-40: "Tribute to a Visionary" [memorial to Sheikh Rashid bin Saeed al Maktoum], October 11, 1990 (Box OS-1, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, Vol. XIV, No. 232: "New era dawning: Zayed" [National Day, 1991], December 3, 1991 (Box OS-1, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, Vol. XXVII, No. 202: "Sheikh Zayed Passes Away,", November 3, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times: Special Issue, "Nation's Homage to Shaikh Zayed", November 3, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, Vol. XXVII, No. 203: "Shaikh Khalifa is named President / Shaikh Zayed laid to rest", November 4, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper sections: Khaleej Times, Vol. XXVII, No. 205: "Chirac calls on Khalifa, offers condolences", November 6, 2004 (Box OS-1, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper supplements: The National: History Project, "Tower of Strength: Qasr al Hosn Through the Ages", February 27, 2013 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Publications and other printed materials, 1977-2014
  - Miscelleneous: Fujairah Municipality. Fujairah Emirate, Tourist Map, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Emirates Dog Breeders Society: Goals and Future Visions, 2009-2012, [no date of publication, circa 2009] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous: Morris, Claude. "The Desert Falcon: the story of H.H. Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan..." (galley proof?), 1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - ADCO: Review for 1978 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - ADCO: [Annual Report], 1979 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - ADCO: Annual Report, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - ADCO: Al Waha magazine, Vol. 32, 2nd quarter, 2014 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - ADCO: Images from the Past, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - ADNOC and its Group of Companies, undated, circa 2010 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - ADPC: Annual Report, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Books: Hellyer, Peter. "Hidden Riches: an archaeological introduction to the United Arab Emirates:" news clippings about, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Books: Hellyer, Peter. "Waves of Time: the marine heritage of the United Arab Emirates:" news cuttings about, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Books: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter (editors). "Jebel Hafeet: a natural history:" editorial correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Serials: "Tribulus," vol. 10:1: photographs and texts submitted to Hellyer for publication, July 2000 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Research and subject files, 1973-2022
  - ADCO book project: materials gathered, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Abu Dhabi International Airport: photographs, design renderings, 2002 and undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Al Nahyan family: geneaologies, clipping, photograph, 1977-2003, and undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Aviation in the U.A.E., 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Donnelly, William (memorial to R.A.F. airman killed in Fujairah during World War II): clippings, 2010 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Handhal, Falih. "A glossary of the dialect of the United Arab Emirates..."(doctoral dissertation, University of Exeter, 1987). Inscribed by author to Hellyer., May 1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Hull, Daniel. "Survey of Documents Relating to H.H. Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al-Nahyan Held by the Government of the United Kingdom at the Public Record Office, London", March 2001 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Pirouz, Mojtahed Zadeh. "The Islands of Tunb and Abu Musa" (Occasional Paper 15, SOAS, London), with Hellyer markings, July 1995 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Postage stamps, UAE: clippings about, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Queen Elizabeth II: memorial publications and programs, 2022 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Trucial Oman Scouts: booklet identifying Arab officers; printed glossaries, documents, undated, circa 1969-1973 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Various, including correspondence, 1992-1998
  - David, Andrew C.H. (relating to publication project about hydrographic surveys of the Gulf), 1998 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Parliament (United Kingdom). House of Commons, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Pugh, Jonathan (University of Aberdeen), 1993 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Steel, David (Member of Parliament): regarding UAE diplomatic relations with Malawi, 1992-1996 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Videocassettes, 1993-2002
  - "The Empty Quarter" (2 copies / cassettes), undated (Box OS-2, Cassette 1)
  - "Searching Through Time," produced by Brooke Films, for ADCO, undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 2)
    Physical characteristics and technical requirements
    TRT 25:48, PAL format
  - "The Liwa: birthplace of Abu Dhabi," ADCO / ADNOC, undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 3)
  - "Land of the Nimr. A community service project sponsored by Shell. " Forth International / Shell Middle East, undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 4)
    TRT 27:00. PAL format
  - "An Environmental Oasis," ERWDA, Abu Dhabi, undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 5)
  - "CNN, Falcon release 1998" [private copy provided to Hellyer, with English and Arabic label] (Box OS-2, Cassette 6)
  - "Sir Wilfred Thesiger visit to the desert" [private copy provided to Hellyer], undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 7)
  - "Orientation for New Comers: Part 1, Get to know your host country." Featuring "Introduction to the U.A.E.," by Peter Hellyer; "U.A.E. Family and Social Life," by Andrea Rugh." With card from U.S. Information Service, and handwritten note from Magda Siebert [?]., September 30, 1993. (Box OS-2, Cassette 8)
  - "Introduction to the History of Abu Dhabi." Lecture by Peter Hellyer to the Emirates Natural History Group, 19 February 2002 (Box OS-2, Cassette 9)
  - "Falcon Release Program--English". PAL format. ERWDA, Abu Dhabi, undated, circa 1998 (Box OS-2, Cassette 10)
  - "Abu Dhabi Archive Material," British Petroleum. With enclosed description, noting that footage was taken by Chris Willy, ADMA Chief Local Representative, between 1962 to 1964, undated copy,circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 11)
  - "Al Ain skeleton video", undated (Box OS-2, Cassette 12)
  - "Peter Hellyer, Abu Dhabi Garden, not complete", undated (Box OS-2, Cassette 13)
  - "Bel Ghelum Island, Sheikh Surour. [From] Body, Ron and Alice" [private copy to Hellyer], 1 February 1996 (Box OS-2, Cassette 14)
    TRT: 0:11:00
  - "Mubarak bin London. Visit to Asab / Shah" [visit of Wilfred Thesiger, private copy provided to Hellyer], circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 15)
  - "Al Yasat and Barn Owl", December 2000 (Box OS-2, Cassette 16)
  - "Abu Dhabi. Hot Fossils. Natural History Museum video" [private copy provided to Hellyer], undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 17)
  - "Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey. Sir Bani Yas Island", undated, circa 1990s (Box OS-2, Cassette 18)
  - "Abu Dhabi, 1969, from Prof. Graham Evans." With accompanying letter from John Murray of the University of Southampton, who sent this video to Hellyer in September 1998. (Box OS-2, Cassette 19)
  - "Between Two Banks." Cultural Foundation, Abu Dhabi, 1999 (Box OS-2, Cassette 20)
    TRT: 0:19:30. PAL